Wherever You Are

WINSTON P. SANDERS (Poul Anderson)

This one, I’m afraid, is a bit confused. The bug-eyed reptilian monster is afraid of the girl, you see, and the hero doesn’t know where he is, much less where the heroine is....

THE monster laid a taloned hand on the girl’s shoulder. She jumped, startled, and whirled about to face bulging red eyes. The monster opened jaws full of teeth that glowed.

The girl wrenched free. "What the devil do you want?” she yelled.

"Eek,” said the monster, stepping back a pace. "Urgu aki, Zivar.”

The girl advanced threateningly. "The next time you forget your manners," she snapped, "the next time you forget who I am, you peasant, may heaven protect you!”

The monster wailed and scuttled down the path, as if hoping the man would come along and save him from the girl. Ulrica Ormstad added a few soldierly oaths and followed. She knew they were wasted; nobody understood any Terrestrial language for several thousand kilometers. (Unless, she thought scornfully, you counted Didymus Mudge. But a corpulent help he was!) Nevertheless, her emotions needed a safety valve, and she could barely speak Harakunye, let alone swear in it. Far down underneath, she admitted her anger stemmed from loneliness. And even, it might be, fear. She was trained to face battle, or storm, or the sudden failure of human engineering under conditions never foreseen by man. The situation here, on this island, held some of those elements. But basically it was another sort of dilemma, involving a worse way to die.

Therefore Ulrica Ormstad fell back on pride. She was a major in the militechnic service of New Scythia, free-born to full rights in Clan Swenson. Let the universe beware!

Long strides carried her quickly through the jungle. Its leaves were stiff and reddish blue: vegetation on Epstein’s Planet photosynthesized, but the compound used was not chlorophyl. At first the pervasive smell had sickened her a little, but she soon grew used to it. Now, when she returned to her home world, or visited Mother Earth—if she ever did —their familiar biochemistry would stink for a while.

The native glowbugs, spectacularly clustered where thickets made a twilight, or the beautiful crystal flowers, or the delicate chiming of bell-fruit, had ceased to interest her. She would swap it all for a chance to leave this hellhole.

The game trail ended and Ulrica stepped out onto a broad white beach. The ship Geyvadigur lay anchored inside a sheltered lagoon: for the hidden sun was close enough to raise considerable tides, even in the absence of a satellite. Boats were drawn up on the sand, where the crew had pitched conical pink tents. The sailor whom she had frightened waited timidly. Doubtless Captain Zalakun wished to question her.

Ulrica sighed. She had gone walking in the jungle just to get away from the endless struggle with Harakunye grammar. For one honest human conversation, in any human language, she would trade her soul.

Make it Swedish, and she’d throw in her sidearm.

Didymus Mudge emerged from one of the tents. He had been playing with a silly-looking affair inside, wooden frameworks and inclined planes, as indeed he had done for a week now. The ship’s carpenter, who had been helping, squeaked at sight of Ulrica and tried to hide behind the man. Since Mudge stood only one hundred eighty centimeters tall, and even the smallest Epsteinian was three meters long including the tail, this was not very successful.

"Oh. Hello.’’ Mudge tried to smile. "What were you doing, Miss Ormstad?”

Ulrica put hands on hips and glared downward. Mudge was slender as well as short, with sandy hair, cowlick, an undistinguished freckled face, and large blue eyes nearsighted behind contact lenses. His tattered gray zipsuit did not make him more impressive.

"I will give you three guesses,” snorted the girl. "I have been making an atomic-powered aircraft with my bare hands? No. Then I have been weaving vines into a radio circuit, to call base and have them come get us? No. I have been practicing to swim all the way to Lonesome Landing? Still no. Kors i Herrans namn! And you are supposed to be bright enough to teach children!”

"I . . . er . . . yes,” said the Earthman meekly.

Ulrica looked him up and down. She herself had the big bones and powerful muscles of a human breed which had spent generations under the gee-and-a-half of New Scythia. It did not make her less graceful, in a full-hipped full-breasted way; on her, a salt-stained tunic and clan kilt looked good. Thick brown braids lay tightly around a face of high cheekbones, straight nose, broad firm mouth, and wide-set green eyes. Even beneath the perpetually leaden sky of this planet, her skin glowed tawny.

"And still Earth manages to be the leader of the League,” she murmured. "I do not understand it. I just plain do not.” Louder: "Well, what have you been tinkering with? Are you making an abstraction ladder in there, to teach semantics? Better you learn to talk with these lizards first!”

"That isn’t my forte,” said Mudge in a defensive tone. "You were trained from childhood to pick up languages fast, tone discrimination, mnemonics— You might as well expect me, at my time of life, to take up ballet, as learn Harakunye from scratch in a week!”

Ulrica laughed.

"What is it?” asked Mudge.

"The thought of you in tights,” she chortled, "doing a pas de deux with an Epsteinian.”

"Some people have a strange sense of humor,” grumbled Mudge. He rubbed his peeling nose. Enough ultraviolet had penetrated the clouds to give his untanned hide a bad sunburn.

"I have been so busy studying,” said Ulrica. Mirth had eased her, and she wanted to offer friendliness to this fellow castaway whom she had scarcely seen so far. "It was necessary I be able to talk with them. As soon as one sailor got restless, I let him go and started with another. I only stopped to eat and sleep. But you, what have you been working on?”

Mudge pointed to his wrist watch. "This was damaged,” he said. "It kept running, and I know the precise time when it was deranged. But now it’s either fast or slow, I’m not sure which. Checking it against my pulse suggests it is slow, but I have always had an irregular pulse. I—”

"What?” yelped Ulrica. "At this time you worry about your little tin watch?”

"It isn’t either,” said Mudge. "It’s a very good seventeen-jewel Swiss chrono. My mother gave it to me at graduation. My graduation, that is, not hers. Though she does have a degree herself, from the same place, Boston Uni—”

"On a desert island,” said Ulrica to heaven, "x thousand kilometers from the one human outpost on this entire planet, surrounded by natives of absolutely unknown culture and intentions, he worries about his graduation present. Du store Gud! Also lieber Gott) nom du Dieu, and Bozhe mot!”

"But wait,” bleated Mudge. "It’s important! Let me explain!”

Ulrica stalked down to the shore, trailing a string of remarks which ionized the air behind her.

The sailor stood patiently at a beached rowboat. He was a typical Epsteinian, which is to say he looked rather like a small slim tyrannosaur with a bulldog face and round cox-combed head. His scales were dark-blue on top, pale below, and zebra striped; his eyes were red and bulging, his teeth phosphorescent yellow. He wore merely crossed belts, one of which held a knife and one a pouch. The data book—thank a lifetime’s Amazonian training for the quickwittedness which had made Ulrica pocket that, along with a bottle of vitamin pills, when the spaceboat exploded—said the autochthones were not actually reptiles, being warmblooded and placental. Neither were they mammals, lacking the appropriate glands as well as hair. They looked ferocious enough, but most of the Geyvadigur crew had shown Yes, Master personalities.

The officers, though, appeared to be something else again.

Ulrica entered the boat. The sailor launched it, jumped in, and rowed her out to the ship. Tension gathered within her. After the captain understood she was working on his language, he had turned the dull job of helping over to his crew. A few hours ago, one of the mates—Ulrica assumed that was their status—had interviewed her briefly and gone off wagging his tail. He must have reported she was now proficient enough to talk intelligently.

The ship loomed over her. Except for the ornate figurehead, it might at first glance have been an early Terrestrial steamer, with high stacks, monstrous sidewheels, and two schooner-rigged masts in case of emergency. Then you began to notice things. There probably wasn’t a door on all Epstein’s Planet, except at Lonesome Landing, likely to pinch a tail. Since the natives sat on those same organs, they had never invented chairs. The treads of all ladders, and the ratlines, were a meter apart. Ulrica had inspected the engines and been surprised to find them oil-burning steam turbines; why the craft then used paddles instead of screws could only be explained by the whimsical gods who, on Earth, had once put engines in the front of rear-wheel drive automobiles.

The Geyvadigur had both magnetic and spring-powered gyro compasses, but otherwise no hint of electromagnetic technology—which scuttled all hope of radioing for help. Quite likely the eternal damp atmosphere accounted for the Harakuni failure to study such phenomena, even though the nearby sun lit every night with fabulous auroras. Poverty of resources, or sheer historical accident, might explain the fact that there were no firearms aboard. The craft did, however, sport catapults, oil bombs, and flame throwers.

Ulrica would have felt better had her own pistol been of any use. But she had exhausted its charge against hungry sea snakes, as she and Mudge paddled their fragment of spaceboat toward this island; and when the vessel went, there hadn’t been time to grab extra clips.

The sailor helped her up a Jacob’s ladder. The decks were littered with his fellows, polishing, holystoning, splicing, the usual nautical chores. A mate stalked about with a barbed- wire whip, touching up an occasional back to encourage progress. Ulrica stamped as haughtily as possible to the captain’s cabin. (Another foreign detail. It was a thatch hut, its walls lined with a tasteful collection of weapons and Epsteinian skulls.)

Captain Zalakun bared his fangs politely as the girl entered. Beside him squatted a gaunt male with an eyeglass and a sash whereon a dozen medals tinkled together. A saw-toothed scimitar lay drawn on the table. Combats between Epsteinians, whose scales bounced back a mere slash, must be awesome.

"Ssss,” greeted the captain. “Coil your tail, Zivar.”

At least he used the aristocratic title. The only alternative Ulrica had found in Harakunye was Yaldazir, which seemed a contraction of a phrase meaning “Offal of an unspeakable worm.” If you weren’t addressed by one title, you necessarily had the other.

She hunkered and waited.

Zalakun turned toward the eyeglass. "Zivar,” he said, "this is the monster called Orumastat, which we took from the sea with its slave four days ago.” He meant Epsteinian days, of course, forty-six hours long. Turning to Ulrica: "Orumastat, this is the most glorious Ieridur of Bera-dura, who heads our expedition. You have not seen him before because he was belowdecks playing karosi. Now that you can talk, Feridur of Bera-dura will let you know his magnanimous will.”

Ulrica struggled to follow the speech. She was by no means fluent in Harakunye. In this conversation, she often had to ask what a word meant; or sometimes the natives were baffled by her accent. But, in effect, she answered: “That would be very pleasant to know.” The language barrier strained out sarcasm. Feridur lifted his monocle. “I say, captain,” he asked, “are you sure it is a bona fide warrior? It didn’t even sneer at me.”

“It claims to be, Zivar,” said Zalakun uncertainly. “And after all, if I may extrude a suggestion, your magnificent memory will recall tribes we have already encountered, prepared to fight bravely but given to soft female-type words on all other occasions.”

“True. Yes. True.” Feridur wiggled his tail tip. “And this creature is still more alien, eh, what? Great Kastakun, how hideous it is!”

“Hey!” bristled Ulrica. Then she sat back. Perhaps this was a compliment. She didn’t know.

According to the data book, all Epsteinians encountered so far by humans had been amiable fishers and farmers. In the archipelagoes fringing the Northeast Ocean they were neolithic; further west, they had begun to use iron; and cursory flights above one of the small continents beyond had shown areas where there were cities and square-rigged ships.

The Geyvadigur was from Harakun, still further west—perhaps at the antipodes—and, apparently, still more advanced in technology. The vessel must have been chugging eastward for months, exploring, refueling often from the planet’s many natural oil wells. Now it poised somewhere near the edge of the Northeast Ocean, with little but water ahead for half the world’s circumference.

In short, this region was as strange to Zalakun and Feridur as it was to Ulrica and Mudge. By the same token, you could no more conclude what the Harakuni were like from reports on local primitives, than an eighteenth-century Martian visiting Hawaii could have predicted the character of Europeans.

It behooved her to gang warily. But gang she must.

"Well, don’t just sit there,” said Feridur. "Speak. Or do tricks, or something.” He yawned. "Great Kastakun! And to think I left my estates because I thought this wretched expedition would be an adventure! Why, I haven’t collected ten decent skulls since we weighed anchor!”

"Ah, but Zivar,” soothed Zalakun, "what an interesting skull Orumastat has.”

"True,” said Feridur, perking up. "Sensational. A collector’s item. That is, if Orumastat gives me enough of a fight.”

"Oh, but it is a guest,” objected Zalakun. "I didn’t mean Orumastat personally, but warriors of its tribe, after we contact them—”

"Quiet, you low creature,” said Feridur.

The captain looked distressed. He tried another approach: "Orumastat may be too soft to be worthwhile. No scales.”

"The erkuma of Akhvadin lacks scales,” pointed out Feridur, "and yet if you meet one hand-to-hand and survive, its skull is jolly well worth fifty like yours.”

"True,” said Zalakun, banging his brow on the table. "I abase myself.”

Ulrica stood up. The conversation seemed to be getting out of hand. "Just a moment, just a moment!” she exclaimed. "I did not come here to fight.”

"No?” Feridur gaped idiotically and twiddled his eyeglass. "Not to fight? Whatever for, then?”

"It was shipwrecked, puissant one,” said Zalakun.

"Eh, what? Shipwrecked? Nonsense. We haven’t had any storms lately. Couldn’t be shipwrecked. I mean to say, that’s nonsense. Come, come, now, monster, out with it. Why are you here?”

"Shut up, you knock-kneed son of a frog!” snarled Ulrica. She kept her fraying temper just enough to say it in English.

"Eh? What say? Don’t understand it. Terrible accent. If it’s going to learn Harakunye, why can’t it learn right? Answer me that.” Feridur leaned back sulkily and toyed with his scimitar.

Zalakun gave him a glance of frustrated exasperation, then said to the girl: "Suppose you explain yourself from the beginning.”

Ulrica had dreaded that request. The upper atmosphere of this planet was so thickly clouded that you never even saw its own sun, let alone the stars. She had learned without surprise that the Harakuni thought their world was flat. Even their boldest sailors never ventured more than a few hundred kilometers from land, and that only in familiar seas where compass and log made crude dead reckoning possible.

Briefly, she was tempted to say: "Mudge and I were coming down in a small ferry from the regular supply spaceship. We were letting the autopilot bring us in on a radio beam, and know only that we were several thousand kilometers west of Lonesome Landing. I have no idea what number that word 'several’ really stands for. Some freakish backblast caused the engine to explode, the jet stream seized us and flung us far off course, we came down in a torn-off section on a dying grav-unit with capricious winds blowing us about, and hit the sea near this island. Every scrap of our equipment is lost or ruined. Doubtless aircraft are hunting for us, but what chance have we of being found on an entire, virtually unmapped planet, before our vitamin pills give out and we die? For we can eat the native life, but unless it is supplemented with Terrestrial vitamins we will soon get scurvy, beriberi, pellagra, and every other deficiency disease you can name.”

But she didn’t have Harakunye words to say it.

Instead, she ventured: "We are of a race different from yours. All our tribe are mighty warriors. We two went far from the island where we live, exploring in a boat that flew. But it suffered harm in the air and we fell here, where you soon found us.”

"We spied your ruin descending and made haste to investigate,” said Captain Zalakun. "I have been looking at the wreckage. That material like unbreakable glass is interesting, but why do you use such soft light metal instead of wood or iron?”

Ulrica sighed. "That is a long story,” she answered. "There are many wonderful things we can show you, if you will only take us to our home.” She was quite confident the Geyvadigur could reach Lonesome Landing in time. The ship must be capable of averaging at least five knots, which meant some fifteen hundred kilometers an Earth-week. The station was certainly less than five thousand kilometers away. There were pills left for three weeks; and, if necessary, several days more without vitamins would do no serious harm.

"We are anxious to know all the nations in your . . . er, in the world,” continued Ulrica persuasively. "We wish trade with them, and friendship.” No need to elaborate on the civilizing program of the League. They might not appreciate that idea without advance propaganda.

"Trade?” Feridur brightened. "Skulls?”

"Well—” temporized Ulrica.

"See here,” said Feridur in a reasonable tone, "either you want to light and give a chap a chance to collect skulls, or else you’re not worth contacting. Eh, what? Isn’t that fair?”

"My splendid master,” said Zalakun with strained politeness, "we have already discovered that few foreign peoples share the interest of us.

Feridur laid talons about the scimitar. His monocle glittered red. "Ssso,” he murmured, "you think that, eh?”

Zalakun wriggled backward on his tail. "Oh, no, your awesomeness,’’ he said hastily. "Not at all. Of course not!”

"Oh, so you do want to expand your own collection,” purred Feridur. He tested saw edges with a thumb. "Well, well! I say! Maybe you would like to add the skull of your liege lord to the museum, eh, what?”

"Oh, no, no, Zivar,” said Zalakun, sweating. "Wouldn’t dream of it.”

"So my skull isn’t good enough for you. Is that it?”

"No, Zivar! Your skull is a thing of beauty.”

"I’ll oblige you any time, you know,” said Feridur. '"We can go ashore right this moment and have a whack at each other, eh?”

Zalakun licked rubbery lips. "Uh,” he said. "Well, the fact is—”

"Ah, I know, I know. Not a drop of sporting blood in the whole dashed ship. Great Kastakun! Well, go on, then, Yaldazir, talk to the monster. Two of a kind.” Feridur yawned elaborately.

Ulrica felt embarrassed for the captain. After breathing hard for a while he resumed the conversation with her. "Where is this home of yours, Orumastat?”

"Somewhere . . . er , . . that way.” Ulrica pointed out the window, past reefs and surf to a steel-gray eastward stretch of sea.

"Can you not be more precise? What archipelago?”

"No archipelago,” said the girl. "It is a single island in the middle of an ocean. My people have seen from the air that the part of the world you must come from has many islands and two small continents, so that one is never far from land. But beyond the region where I think we are now, there is almost no land for ... I don’t know your measures. You could sail steadily for more than fifty of your days before seeing shore again.”

"I say!” Feridur straightened. "You’re sure, monster?”

"Not in detail,” Ulrica admitted. "But I do know there is that much water somewhere to the east, ahead of you.”

"But then . . . Great Kastakun, captain! I’m glad we found that out! We’re heading straight homeward again!”

"To be sure,” declared Zalakun, appalled. "Why, after so long a time at sea, one could not even guess at northward or southward drift. One might miss the shore you speak of completely. Even if the wind didn’t fail in so long a voyage. For we could only steam twenty days at most before our oil bunkers were dry.”

"It would not be that far to my island,” said Ulrica.

"Hm-m-m . . . how far?”

"I am not certain. But no more than, uh, fifteen days.”

"Fifteen days in open ocean!” gasped Zalakun.

He sat back, tongue hanging out, speechless with horror. Feridur quizzed Ulrica through his monocle. "But I say,” he objected, "what’s the jolly old purpose in living so far away? Eh? It’s unheard of. I mean to say, nobody lives in midocean.”

"Since we can fly at great speeds, we are not inconvenienced by distance,” replied Ulrica. And colonizing an isolated speck would offend no natives: they didn’t even realize it existed. No sense, though, in giving so pacifistic a reason to this warrior culture.

"But how do you find your way? Eh? Answer me that. Ha, ha, I've bally well got you there!” Feridur wagged a triumphant finger.

Ulrica decided that there was also no point in describing a radio net involving three small artificial satellites. "We have our methods,” she said in a mysterious tone.

"By the Iron Reefs,” murmured Zalakun. His tone held awe. "Of course you do! You must, or you couldn’t have found that island in the first place. But to know exactly where you are, even when there’s no land in sight, no current or cloud formations or— Why, that’s a secret sought for as long as there have been ships!”

"We will gladly provide you with similar means,” said Ulrica. "If, of course, you take us home.”

"Naturally!” babbled Zalakun. He sprang to his feet, wagging his tail till the air whistled. "Jumping gods, master, what’re a thousand bug-bitten skulls next to a prize like that? Just give us a line, Zivar Orumastat, give us a compass bearing and we’ll hold true on it till you’re home, though the sky fall down!”

"Ah, nej!” whispered Ulrica. She felt the blood sink from her face.

"What is it?” asked the captain. He came around the table and offered an arm. She leaned on it, badly in need of support.

"I just realized ... I was so busy before that it only occurs to me now ... I know where the island is,” she said faintly. "But I can’t give you a course. I don’t know where we are!”

When Ulrica had gone aboard ship, Ardabadur, the carpenter, followed. There he directed a gang of sailors as they unloaded the completed Foucault bob, got it into a boat and ashore. While they carried it onward, he went to the tent where Didymus Mudge was at work.

He hesitated outside. The Earthling’s operations had been fascinating, but enigmatic and delicate. Ardabadur didn’t want to interrupt. Finally he stuck his head through the flap.

Mudge stood hunched over his apparatus. In the days since arriving here, he had gotten it to function rather well. Oh, more accurately, Ardabadur had. They shared no words, but through gestures, drawings, and crude models Mudge had explained what he needed. Then the ship’s excellent carpenter shop had prepared it for him—after which he tinkered, groaned, and sent it back for revision.

A ball of cast bronze rolled thunderously down an inclined plane. Mudge watched it while counting the swings of a small pendulum, carefully made from a leather cord and a lead weight in a leveled glass-sided box. When the ball reached ground, Mudge made a note. The Harakuni had paper and pencils. "Which is a mercy,” he said aloud. "But why couldn’t you have brought a clock along?”

Ardabadur hopped inside and squatted respectfully. Mudge ran a hand through rumpled hair and mopped sweat off his face. "I’m sure you have some chronometry,” he said. "You have probably even measured the length of the day, and its seasonal variation. I know the long twilight confuses things, clouds always hiding the sun . . . but if you averaged enough observations for enough centuries, you could do it. So why didn’t you bring a clock? Knowing this planet’s rotation period, I could have corrected my watch according to your timepiece by simple arithmetic.”

He tapped the chrono on his wrist. "I think a momentary surge of magnetism must have affected it,” he went on. "It’s antimagnetic, to be sure, but a disintegrating nuclear field can produce overwhelming forces. I suppose I’m lucky to be alive at all. Well, I know from the data book how long from sunrise to sunrise, so theoretically I could use that fact to tell me how fast or slow my watch is. But in practice, the clouds complicate observation too much for anything like accuracy; and I haven’t got a hundred years in which to accumulate enough data for analysis.”

Ardabadur wagged his tail knowingly, as if he understood English.

"Of course, time is of no obvious importance to you on shipboard,” said Mudge. "Since you can’t make astronomical sightings, and you don’t even know astronomical phenomena exist, you cannot have invented navigation. You possess an inaccurate little hourglass to tell you when to change watch, and that’s all.”

He smiled, a weary lopsided grimace. "Well, I’ve gotten around the handicap,” he said. "This makes my one-thousandth observation of time to roll down the plane. After calculation, I should be able to work out a very good correction factor for my watch.” He patted the bulge in one hip pocket. "Do you know, my friend, I owe my life to whoever invented waterproof paper. Without it, the data book would be unreadable. It was a wet journey to this island. And this book compiles—not only the physical and mathematical constants needed anywhere in the universe—but all the information so far gathered about Epstein’s Planet. Its mass, dimensions, orbital elements, rotational period, axial inclination, surface gravity, atmospheric composition, everything—or almost everything. Unfortunately, such quantities as magnetic deviation have hardly been mapped at all: otherwise I might try using that to locate us. The book does include tide tables, though, not only for Lonesome Landing but for several other selected spots, at which temperature, pelagic salinity, and whatever else occurred to the expeditions, have been measured.” He turned toward the exit. "But I am sure you came to show me something,” he said. "Forgive me. I talk too much. However, it has been a very trying week on this island. I am used to talking, the feast of reason and the flow of soul and so on. My mother has always moved in intellectual circles. And then, I am a teacher by profession: basic science in the elementary grades.”

Ardabadur led the way over the beach. Didymus Mudge continued to chatter. Perhaps he wanted to drown out the surf. Now, with the incoming solar tide, it had grown loud, an undergroundish sinister noise to his landlubber ears. Overhead scudded smoky rainclouds, and lightning flickered, high up in the permanent gray layers. The jungle talked in the wind with a million blue tongues.

"My mother was very dubious about my coming to Epstein’s Planet,” he said. "I had never been farther than Luna before, and then I had letters of recommendation to people she knows. On the other hand, it was an undeniable opportunity. The scientific and cultural staff here is already of respectable size, and is due for great expansion in the near future, when intensive work begins. The tendency is for married couples to be employed, and they have children, and the children need education. On a four-year contract, I could not only save a very good salary, but make valuable friendships among highly intellectual people, if only my mother could have come too, I would never have hesitated. But no opening was available for her. She finally agreed that I had a duty to my career.”

Mudge looked around. He saw nothing but drifting sand, tents that snapped in the wind, waves and the alien ship. He leaned close to Ardabadur and hissed:  "Frankly, and don’t tell anyone, I thought it was high time I went somewhere by myself. I am thirty years old. After all!”

Then, blushing and stammering, he hurried on: "Miss . . . er . . . Major Orumastat isn’t an instructor. Not of children, I mean. She was to organize defensive squads for the exploration teams, in case they meet hostility. Not that we would dream of provoking any such demonstration, I assure you. But—”

But by that time they had reached the Foucault bob, where a dozen sailors waited for orders. Ardabadur beamed like a picket fence and waved a hand at his creation.

Mudge examined it with care. It was as he had drawn, a hollow copper ball some one hundred and fifty centimeters across. When filled with sand, its mass would be enormous. A small loop and a very light stiff wire were affixed to the bottom. On top was a larger loop, riveted to ten meters of wire rope. As far as Mudge could see, it had been made with perfect symmetry and should give no trouble.

He said aloud: "We shall have to wait for calm weather. The wind would cause the pendulum to describe an ellipse today. But according to the data book, this region at this time of year is usually calm, so we can doubtless perform the experiment tomorrow. Let us set it all up now.”

Ardabadur got his drift and barked orders. His assistants sprang to work. The sphere lay under a tall tree on the beach’s edge which had been stripped of branches. A stout gallowslike crosspiece had been erected on the trunk, thirteen meters above ground. Now a pair of sailors swarmed up and affixed the loose end of the cable, so that the copper ball hung suspended. It swayed and toned in the wind. Mudge was gratified to note that it had little tendency to move in arcs; Ardabadur’s suspension was well designed.

"Why are you helping me?’’ he mused aloud. "You have certainly spared no pains on my behalf, though you can have no idea why I want all this work done. Is it curiosity? Or boredom? For this has been a long dull time for you to lie anchored—I suppose on our account, until your captain knows more about us. I prefer to think you feel a genuine friendship and wish to assist a being in distress. Your officers seem to be perfect brutes, but all you common crewpeople are very quiet and well-behaved. I am sure you are capable of empathy.”

"Uru’s kalka kisir,” said the Epsteinian.

"Oh,” said Mudge.

Hanging the pendulum took at least an hour. At the end, though, he had it well adjusted. As the bob passed the lowest point of its arc, the cat’s-whisker wire on the bottom traced a thin line in sand which had been smoothed, leveled, and wet down. Now Mudge led the sailors away; they raised the ball again and carried it to another preselected tree. Here the human mounted a ladder, knotted a piece of light rope to the bottom loop, and tied the other end to the bole. The sphere hung four meters above ground, its cable nearby, taut, ready to swing when released

"Now we fill the globe with sand to make it heavier and thus more stable,” said Mudge, "and then I believe we can, er, call it a day.”

He demonstrated. The sailors formed a bucket brigade up the ladder and began loading the ball. They had almost completed that task when Ulrica Ormstad appeared.

Behind her trailed Captain Zalakun and a bemedaled, besworded, bemonocled Epsteinian whom Mudge had not seen before. Ardabadur whistled and fell on his face. The sailors tumbled from the ladder and followed suit. Mudge gaped.

"Good heavens,” he said.

"This is Feridur of Beradura,” ex plained the girl. “He owns this expedition. I mean that almost literally.”

Her face was tight and anxious Though the wind blew cool, there was sweat on her wide brow, and an uncharacteristic lock of hair had broken loose to stream over one ear

"Mudge,” she said, "we are in trouble.”

"I know,” he agreed.

Her temper ripped across. "Don’t get sarcastic with me, you little worm!” she yelled.

"But I wasn’t ... I didn’t—” Mudge swallowed. Ulrica was a beautiful sight, he thought. So, however, was a hungry tiger.

He had had no experience with the modern frontier type of woman. His mother disapproved of them. In his inmost soul he admitted hoping he would meet a young lady on this planet, where no one would jealously interfere, who could become Mrs. Mudge. But someone well-bred and well-read, with civilized ways, please!

"What have you been doing, anyhow?” snapped Ulrica.

"I told you,” said Mudge, after husking once or twice. "I have been correcting my watch. I have a correction factor now, or will as soon as I make the calculations from my data, and then we will know exact Greenwich time.” He paused. "I admit that is making no allowance for relativistic laws . . . simultaneity is an approximational concept at best . . . but this is a refinement which the data book does not take into account either. So—”

"Shut your big mouth before I reach in and pull you inside out!” screamed Ulrica.

Mudge cowered.

Ulrica expressed herself richly for several seconds. Mudge would have covered his ears, but was too stunned. He had never heard most of those words. The context, though, made their meaning all too hideously evident. Good heavens! Cultivated society, conversing at tea time in Boston, seemed five hundred light-years away.

He remembered with a shock that it was five hundred light-years away.

A part of him gibbered that the spaceship had headed into Virgo, and surely people would not make remarks like this in the region of Virgo.

Reason came back to him as Ulrica ran down. She put arms akimbo and said grimly: "All right. Why do you want to know Greenwich Market Time? To say your evening prayers?”

"No,” gulped Mudge. "To locate us. I mean, we have to know where we are, don’t we? The data book says Lonesome Landing is at 47° 32' 4" N., and the prime meridian has been drawn through it. But we know only that we are somewhere west of there, how far we cannot tell, and have no idea if we are north or south of it. I mean—”

"You mean,” growled Ulrica, "that you have read chronometric time is necessary for navigation. So you set blindly out to find the time. You gruntbrain! Don’t you know longitude reckoning depends on the comparison of times? How can we get local noon when we can’t see the sun ? How can we get the height of anything, for latitude?”

She gave the copper ball a green glare. "And what, with your kind permission, is that?”

"A ... a Foucault pendulum,” said Mudge. He squared thin shoulders. "It is a classic demonstration of the fact that a planet rotates. A pendulum will hold to its own vibrational plane—in effect, the planet turns beneath it—so that cat whisker will describe a line which gradually turns through a complete circle.” Ulrica stood speechless.

"This project has a secondary value,” continued Mudge with a bit more self-confidence, “in that I am sure these Epsteinians imagine their world to be flat and fixed in space. The pendulum offers a simple proof of its rotation. Therefore they will be more inclined to accept on faith our assertion that the planet is a spheroid, and this in turn will lead them to follow our advice when—”

"Great,” said Ulrica. "Leaping. Blue. Balls. Of. Radioactive. Muck.”

Then the blast came. Mudge huddled away from it. The girl raged over his head, like the remote lightning come down to earth.

"For your blank blank information, Mister Didymus Blank Blank Mudge, I have just been talking to the captain and Feridur. They don’t know which dash deleted asterisk way to steer for the obscenity station. How could they? Without a reasonably accurate vector—distance within a few hundred kilometers, direction within a compass point or less—they could search the double dash four star exclamation point ocean for an anathematized year without coming near Lonesome Blank Blank Landing. And of course they won’t even attempt it. If they cruised obscenely around in any kind of crudely expressed search pattern, they’d lose their own unprintable way and risk never finding land again. If we don’t give them a deep blue bearing and a sulfurous distance estimate, they’re going to up anchor and head for accursed home tomorrow. AND YOU WANT TO GIVE A LECTURE ON COPERNICAN ASTRONOMY!”

"Oooh,” moaned Ardabadur, trembling.

Exactly, thought Mudge, also trembling.

He opened his mouth, but nothing came out. At that moment, Feridur twittered. Ulrica stopped in midcareer and faced around. Feridur put the monocle in his eye and repeated the question. Captain Zalakun said something in a protesting tone of voice. Feridur made a sweet reply at which the captain shuddered and backed away. Ulrica turned quite pale.

Mudge listened intently. He heard Feridur ask, with painful distinctness: "JJluka’s kuruta yaldazir itoban urnalik ?”

"Yalgesh, Zirvan,” said Ulrica, in a small subdued voice and a Swedish accent. "Obunadun baladur erkedi- vir.”

The saw-toothed blade rasped from Ferdidur’s sheath. He giggled. "Yagatun!”

Ulrica clenched her fists. Then, suddenly, she spat at the Harakuni’s feet. The color flamed back in her cheeks. "Yagatun zoltada, Yaldazir Fridur!” she snapped.

"Eep!” said Feridur, horrified at such manners. Captain Zalakun sought to remedy the breach, but got nowhere. The sailors burrowed in the sand, trying to make themselves inconspicuous. Finally Zalakun himself went off in giant kangaroo leaps toward the tents.

"What is this?” whispered Mudge.

Ulrica said in a harsh tone: "Feridur wanted to know if you can locate the Earth base, since I can’t. When I admitted you had only been playing games, he said he would fight me. I have explained that the vitamin pills are necessary for our life, so he knows we would soon die in any case when he turns homeward. He wants to take my skull in combat instead, for his collection.”

"What?” squeaked Mudge. The island revolved around him. He stumbled, feeling blackness in his head. Ulrica caught him.

"Don’t be afraid,” she said in the same metallic voice. "You are not worth fighting—no glory in taking your head. They will keep you for a pet, I suppose . . . and you will have my pills . . . and it is barely possible, in that extra time a search party will chance upon you.”

"But this is ghastly!” stammered Mudge. "I mean, it isn’t done!”

“It seems to be.” Ulrica managed a bleak grin. "Maybe I can take Feridur’s head. Then I inherit his titles, properties, and skull collection, and can sail the ship where I will. Not that we have much chance anyway, without a bearing.” She sighed. "This may be the better way to die.”

"But listen—” wailed Mudge. Zalakun returned with a sword, shouldered past him and said something to the girl. She nodded. Mudge tried to get a word in edgewise. "Shut up,” said Ulrica. Zalakun finished by handing her the weapon.

"In case you are interested,” said Ulrica, "he was explaining the rules. In effect, there aren’t any. Either party can use tricks, assistants—” Zalakun flickered a glance at Feridur, who was polishing his monocle several meters off. The captain leaned over and whispered something to the girl. She smiled a suddenly gentle smile and gave his scaly back a furtive pat.

"What is it?” gibbered Mudge. "What did he say?”

"He said no one will help Feridur,” she answered curtly. "They don’t like him. Of course, they are too afraid of him to take my side either. He’s the leading phrenologist in Harakun.”

"But ... I can ... I mean, that is, I have to tell you—

"Oh, be quiet,” she said. "What use would you be? Stand aside out of my way, that is all you can do.”

"But you don’t have to fight this barbaric thing!” yelped Mudge. "It isn’t necessary! If you would only listen to me for five minutes, I can explain—”

"Shut up,” she cut him off. He tried to continue. She whirred her blade past his nose. He jumped backward, choking. She laughed with a real, if deplorably coarse mirth, and said more kindly: "It is too late anyhow. I insulted him on purpose. Whatever I said now, he would insist on disposing of me.”

Zalakun wrung her hand and scuttled off to the sidelines as Feridur turned around. The aristocrat screwed his eyeglass' in more firmly, hefted his sword, and minced across the sand. Ulrica crouched, waiting. The wind fluttered her kilt and the one loose lock of hair.

Mudge put his back against the tree bole and tried to think. But that was like trying to run through glue. This was the U.S.P. Standard adventure-story situation, a beautiful girl threatened by a bulging-eyed monster, and he was a man, and it was up to him to save her, but—Feridur’s blade whipped up and then down. It hit Ulrica’s with a clang that hurt Mudge’s eardrums. The blow would have gone halfway through him.

He huddled next to the comforting bulk of good old Ardabadur, and prayed that the beautiful girl would save him from the bug-eyed monster.

"Yava’s!” cried Feridur.

He bounced back from Ulrica’s attack. She knew fencing, but had no skill with these awkward weapons. She closed in, though, a rush and a sweep. Somehow it got past Feridur’s guard, and steel teeth rattled across his scales. They did no harm. His own blade moved with a combination of thrust and stroke. Ulrica retreated, fending him off by mere fury of blows. He grinned and stalked around her, so that she must keep turning to face him. His reach was not much greater than hers, but he had every advantage of height, stride, and strength.

All at once, like a snake, his weapon darted in, slid past Ulrica’s and touched her thigh. She got away in time, with only a thin red slash, but Mudge felt sick. "Son of an improper union,” she muttered, and cut loose again. "You want to saw me up alive, huh? We’ll see!”

She leaped in, hewing low. Feridur hissed as she opened a gash on his left shin. Her metal was already up to block his answering cut. He brought his edge down, chopping at her ankles. She jumped high, the sword whined beneath her feet, she came down on it and it was torn from Feridur’s grasp.

"Now, you miserable alligator!” she exclaimed, and assaulted his head. A small sailor emitted a very small cheer, then covered his mouth and looked around in terror of having been overheard.

Feridur whirled about, raised his tail, and struck Ulrica amidships. The wind whoofed from her. She rolled three meters and climbed dizzily to her feet. Feridur picked up his sword and advanced with deliberation. The watching sauroids looked distressed, Captain Zalakun twisted his hands together, but all seemed nailed to the spot.

"Lookout!” screamed Mudge. Impulsively, he darted forward.

Ulrica waved him back. She still clutched her sword. The free hand dabbed at a bruised cheek. "No,” she said. "One is enough.”

"But you are a woman!” he cried. "Give me that! I’ll fight for you!” She managed a ghost of a laugh. "Dear little Didymus,” she whispered. "I am an Ormstad of Clan Swenson. Get out of my way.” Feridur closed in for the kill as Mudge staggered back to Ardabadur’s side. The Harakuni noble paused to readjust his monocle. He tittered.

Then Ulrica exploded into motion. Her sword became a blur, yelled in the air, banged on Feridur’s iron, knocked down his guard and slashed him across the shoulder. He hissed and jumped back. Ulrica followed, shouting.

She’s splendid! thought Mudge wildly. They don’t make girls like that in Boston! He blushed and corrected himself: I mean, there aren’t any girls like that in Boston.

Feridur rallied and beat off the attack. Ulrica retreated. Through wind and surf,, above the steady belling of steel, Mudge could hear how she clawed for breath. And once she stumbled from exhaustion. Feridur would kill her in minutes.

"I should go out and die with her.” Mudge licked dry lips. "Really, I should, if I can’t do anything else. I feel so useless.”

"Akrazun kulakisir,” said Ardabadur comfortingly.

"It wouldn’t be against the rules,” chattered Mudge. "She told me anything goes. I could help. Only . . .only ... to be absolutely honest, as my mother always told me to be, I’m scared.”

Feridur drew blood again: a flesh wound, no more, but Ulrica’s sword was now slow arid heavy in her fingers.

"Of course, later I can explain, and maybe they will take me to Lonesome Landing after all,” babbled Mudge. "But no, I haven’t her training, I could not possibly learn the language before my vitamins ran out. I am done for, too. You had all this work for nothing, Ardabadur. Now you will never know why you made—”

The thought came to him. It was not exactly a blinding flash of intuition. Or perhaps it was. He didn’t notice. By the time he was fully conscious of having an idea, it was already in execution.

"Ulrica!” he shouted. "Miss Ormstad! Major Ormstad! Get him . . . maneuver him onto . . . that cleared, wet space in the sand . . . under that tree . . . keep him there . . . and look out!”

Meanwhile he snatched a knife from Ardabadur’s belt and went up the ladder. The carpenter whistled alarm and started after him. Frantically, Mudge kicked him on the crest, while sawing at the cord and yelling at Ulrica.

"Miss Ormstad! Work him onto that level damp patch! Quickly! Hold him . . . just a minute . . . please! I beg of you!”

Ulrica, fighting for another second of existence, heard his thin screech and croaked out of pain and despair: "Let me die by myself, Earthling.”

Somehow, without planning to, scarcely aware of it, Didymus Mudge inflated his lungs and roared in a heroic tenor, so that even Zalakun jumped: "Profanity dash blasphemy blue and green, green starred et cetera! Do what I blank unprintable tell you before I commit unspeakable violence upon your defamity person!"

Whether the memory of drill sergeants ten years ago came back and possessed her, or whether she was suddenly given hope—or for whatever reason—Ulrica sprang away from Feridur and ran. He bounded after, jeering at her. Ulrica crossed the wet sand, twirled about, and met his charge. Saw teeth locked together as the blades met. Feridur began to shove hers aside. She threw her last strength into resisting him, though she felt it drain from muscle and bone.

Didymus Mudge cut the cord on his Foucault sphere.

Loaded with hundreds of kilos of sand, it swung across the beach, gathering velocity all the way. Mudge fell off the ladder, onto Ardabadur. They went down in a tangle of arms, legs, and tail. By the time he had picked himself up, it was all over, and the Harakuni were howling as one jubilant mob around Ulrica.

Mudge limped toward her. He wanted to see, if he could, how much of an arc his pendulum was describing. Yes . . . there was definitely an elliptical path, but a narrow one. That tendency should be quite obviated when he made the official experiment tomorrow. He would burn the rope then, rather than cut it, to liberate the bob without transverse forces . . . He ducked as it whistled past. So huge a thing had not lost much energy when it hit Feridur.

Mudge saw what had happened to Feridur. For a while he was not a well man.

Captain Zalakun released Ulrica’s hand, which he had been pumping in a most Earthlike fashion, and regarded the mess. Finally he shook his head and clicked his tongue. "Dear me, Zlvar Orumastat,” he said. "You really must chastise your slave. No doubt he meant well, but he has completely ruined what would have been a very fine egg-shaped skull.”

A while afterward, when they sat in the captain’s cabin, eating the Epsteinian food—which humans found dreary—and drinking the Epsteinian wine—which was forty proof and not bad at all—Zalakun asked Ulrica: "Arvadur zilka itoban urnalik?”

The girl blinked beautiful, through slightly blurred green eyes above her goblet, in Mudge’s direction. "He wants to know if you can indeed navigate us, Didymus,” she said.

Mudge blushed. "Well, not exactly,” he admitted. "Until we reach base and get a radio network receiver, I mean. But then he will be able to navigate himself. Ahem!” He burped and reached for his own cup. "I can, however, tell him to a fair approximation how far away Lonesome Landing is, and in what direction. That should suffice, since he has good compasses and is independent of the wind. Rather, I will be able to tell him this tomorrow, when I have all the data and finish the calculations.”

"But how?” She leaned forward. "How, Didymus?” she repeated softly.

"Well,” he said after catching his breath, "the data book gives the location of base, so if I know our present coordinates, it becomes a simple problem in spherical trigonometry, for which the book supplies tables, to determine—”

"Yes, yes,” she said in a slightly less worshipful tone. "But how do you locate us?”

"It is a problem of finding latitude and longitude,” he said. He took another swig of wine. It buzzed in his head, but helped steady his voice. Once he got going, the lecture habits of a decade took over and he talked automatically. "Ahem! We had the data book and a watch, but the watch had been running awry since the moment of the crash, so that I no longer knew within several hours what time it was. Now if I could only observe something which took a precisely known time, such as ten seconds, I could compare the watch, see by what factor it was fast or slow, and apply the correction.

"I looked up the standard value of Epsteinian gravity, one thousand twelve centimeters per second squared. Local variations would not make any significant difference. A pendulum describing short arcs has a period which is a function only of length and gravity. The carpenter made me a good small pendulum and I clocked it.”

"Yes, but,” said Ulrica. She paused. "But,” she repeated muzzily. Wine had hidden her own weariness from her, but it made the wine all the more effective. "But you don’t know the length of the pendulum. Not with, urp, precision.”

"No,” said Mudge. "However, the distance covered by a falling body is a function only of gravity and time. Air resistance can be disregarded for low speeds. I repeated Galileo’s experiment, dropping a weight through a fixed height. Actually, I rolled it down an inclined plane—so did he —to get a greater length and thus a smaller percentage of error. Though I did not know the effective height in Absolute units, I took care to see that it was an integral multiple of the pendulum length; and I measured the time for a ball to roll down in terms of pendulum oscillations. I therefore have two equations in two unknowns, easy to solve. When I have computed all my data, taking the average of many observations, I will know the length of the pendulum in centimeters and, what I really wanted, the length of its period in seconds. From this I can correct the time shown by my watch.”

Ulrica smiled, stretched out on the floor and laid her head on Mudge’s lap.

"Goodness gracious!” Mudge gasped. "What are you doing, Miss Ormstad?”

"You were speaking about falling bodies,” she murmured.

"But ... I mean . . . Major Ormstad !”

"Ulrica is my name,” she whispered.

Zalakun’s leathery face assumed an avuncular expression. He said something which Mudge was afraid meant, "Bless you, my children.”

"Well,” gulped Mudge. "Well, if you’re tired, Miss . . . er . . . Major ... I can find a pillow.”

"I’m quite comfy,” said the girl. She reached up and patted his cheek. "I’m sorry for losing my temper. I wouldn’t have if I had known you better, Didymus. Know what? You’re cute.”

Mudge ran a finger beneath his collar and plunged terror-stricken onward: "Since this planet has only solar tides, I was spared one complication. To be sure, tidal patterns are not simple; but a wave crossing the almost empty Northeast Ocean will not be much delayed either. To further help me, the data book has tide tables not only for Lonesome Landing, but for selected spots elsewhere. This will assist interpolation. In short, when my watch has been corrected, I will be able to identify any local tide as one which passed Lonesome Landing so-and-so many hours ago. Knowing the speed at which it travels, I thereby know how far westward it has come in that interval—hence, our longitude.”

Ulrica frowned, with a finger laid to her chin. "No,” she said, " 'cute’ is the wrong word. I mean, you are cute, but you are also very much of a manfolk. When you shouted at me to do what you wanted, it was poetic. Like a saga.”

"I forgot myself,” said Mudge wretchedly.

"I’ll help you forget some more,” beamed Ulrica.

"Ugvan urunta,” said Zalakun.

Mudge interpreted this as a request to continue his discourse. "Latitude is a simpler problem, solvable with greater accuracy,” he said very fast. "I know the angular velocity of this planet’s rotation, three hundred sixty degrees in forty-six hours. Knowing the date, I could calculate latitude from length of daylight, except for the clouds. A Foucault pendulum affords a much better method. It would not turn at all at the equator; it would turn with maximum speed at either pole; in between, the rate is a sine function of latitude. I can use geometrical constructions to mark off a precise angle such as ninety degrees, clock the time the pendulum needs to sweep through this angle, and thence compute our latitude. And, and, and that’s all,” he finished. "I should have the information for you by nightfall tomorrow, and we can start out next day. To be sure, accumulated uncertainties will doubtless, cause us to miss the island, but not by much. We can find it in time if we scout about. Though I suppose we need only come within a few hundred kilometers to be spotted by an aircraft—”

Ulrica chuckled. "And so we will arrive as great heroes,” she said, "very romantic, and perhaps we had better not disappoint people about the romantic side of it, no? Kdre lille Didymus. This is going to be so pleasant a sea voyage.”

Mudge swallowed hard and wondered how to escape.

"lstvaz tuli,” said Zalakun with a fatuous smirk.

Mudge threw him a look of wild appeal, as if somehow the bug-eyed monster could save the man from the girl.